Ralph K. James Papers
Ralph K. James Papers
1942-1968
James, Ralph Kirk.
4.0 linear ft.
American naval officer, engineer. Collection includes correspondence (1947-1958); speeches; a diary kept during a mission to French West Africa in 1942; and printed material.
149080
Biographical History
Ralph Kirk James (1907 or 1908-1994) was an American naval officer who retired with the rank of rear admiral. Admiral James had master's degrees in naval architecture and marine engineering. Among his other career achievements, he served with the Bureau of Ships in French West Africa and was commander of the Long Beach Naval Shipyard and chief of the Navy's Bureau of Ships.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Ralph K. James Papers consist of personal and quasi-official correspondence dating from 1947; many speeches ranging from technical seminar papers to humorous banquet toasts; and a diary kept during a naval mission to French West Africa in 1942.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; James, Ralph Kirk.; United States. -- Navy -- Officers.; Marine engineering.; Marine engineers -- United States.; Military engineers -- United States.; Africa, West.; United States -- History, Military.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Speeches (documents); Military engineers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- General files
  - ABC's of Shipbuilding (Box 1)
  - Accident, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Advisory Committee on Fiscal Organization and Procedures, 1954 (Box 1)
  - American Society of Naval Engineers, Inc., 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Armed Forces Journal (Box 1)
  - Biography (Box 1)
  - Building Naval Ships Against Time (Box 1)
  - Citations and commendations (Box 1)
  - Complimentary letters (Box 1)
  - Congratulatory letters, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Class of 1928, Annapolis, 1948-1968; 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Personal
      - 1951-1954, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - 1955-1963, 12 folders (Box 2)
    - Quasi-official
      - 1947-1955, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1955-1958, 8 folders (Box 3)
    - Society of Naval Architects and Marine Engineers, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Diary, mission to French West Africa, 1942 (Box 3)
  - Farewell (Box 3)
  - Fleet Maintenance and Battle-Damage Repairs in the Pacific During World War II, manuscript and brochure (Box 3)
  - Fourth Twenty-Eighter, USNA '28 (Box 3)
  - International conference, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Laws, staff work (Box 3)
  - Long Beach Naval Shipyard subsidence (Box 3)
  - Long Beach Naval Shipyard, Surface Subsidence and Remedial Measures (Box 3)
  - Pat's wedding (Box 4)
  - Prospectus, US Naval Shipbuilding Activity Schedule (Box 4)
  - Resume (Box 4)
  - Scheduling paper (Box 4)
  - Society of Naval Architects and Marine Engineers
    - General (Box 4)
    - Diamond Jubilee, 1968; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Speeches, 1954-1967; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Submarine design study group (Box 4)
  - Tickle (Box 4)
  - Travel vouchers (Box 4)